Guide to the Files and manuscripts regarding Frances (Fanny) D'Arusmont Wright, 1746-1967.
Wright, Frances (Fanny) D'Arusmont, Files and manuscripts regarding
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Files and manuscripts regarding Frances (Fanny) D'Arusmont Wright, 1746-1967.
6934
Wolfson, Theresa,
3.7 cubic ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Include correspondence (1909-1967) chiefly between Wolfson and Perkins, researchers, and various research institutions seeking biographical, geneological and publication data on Frances Wright.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Research materials and manuscripts collected by Wolfson for the book Frances Wright: Free Inquirer, published in 1939, which Wolfson co-authored with A. J. G. (Alice Gray) Perkins.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Include correspondence (1909-1967) chiefly between Wolfson and Perkins, researchers, and various research institutions seeking biographical, geneological and publication data on Frances Wright; drafts (mss. typewritten) of the book chapters, index, and bibliography; biographical data on Wright consisting of mss. notes; excerpts and drafts. The excerpts (mss.) were copied chiefly by Perkins from letters of Wright and from the newspapers New Harmony Gazette (1825-1828) and Free Inquirer (1828-1831). Wright's correspondents include Richard Wright, Mrs. Craig Millar, Charles Wilkes, James Milne, the Marquis de Lafayette, William Roscoe, B. Flower, Jeremy Bentham, Robert Dale Owen, Camilla Wright, Phiquepal D'Arusmont, and Marie Louise Duclos Fretageot. Also excerpts from the poetry of Wright, Wright's Commonplace Book, Owen's diary, and the Book of Nashoba kept by James Richardson and Sylvie D'Arusmont's diary (child of Wright and Phiquepal D'Arusmont).
Also original mss. speeches and lectures of Wright: The 6 Epochs of Human History (history of human civilization: its beginning in India, Egypt, Greece, and Rome and its later phases in medieval and modern Europe); View of the Political Horizon (1838); Free Public Speech: The Clarion of Popular Liberty (1838); an account of Wright's ideal America (1839); a lecture on religion (n.d.); a lecture (no title) delivered at the Masonic Hall in New York (1839); 4 other untitled lectures; and 16 volumes of lectures.
Also, the published writings of Wright, photocopies of lithographs, and clippings.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wolfson, Theresa, 1897-1972,; Bentham, Jeremy, 1748-1832.; Bentham, Jeremy, 1748-1832; D'Arusmont, Phiquepal (William Phiquepal).; D'Arusmont, Phiquepal (William Phiquepal); D'Arusmont, Sylvie; D'Arusmont, Sylvie.; Flower, George, 1788-1862.; Flower, George, 1788-1862; Fretageot, Marie Louise Duclos, -1833.; Fretageot, Marie Louise Duclos, -1833; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier, Marquis de, 1757-1834.; Millar, Mrs. Craig; Millar, Mrs. Craig.; Milne, James, 1981-; Milne, James.; Owen, Robert Dale, 1801-1877.; Owen, Robert Dale, 1801-1877; Richardson, James; Richardson, James.; Roscoe, William; Roscoe, William.; Wright, Camilla; Wright, Camilla.; Wright, Frances, 1795-1852.; Wright, Frances, 1795-1852; Wright, Richard, 1794-; Wright, Richard, 1794-
Subjects:
Feminists -- United States.; Feminists
Places:
United States
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Related collection: 5136, 5216.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Box 1
Correspondence between Wolfson and Perkins and also with various research institutes.
Series II. Drafts
Boxes 2-5
Work copies of various chapters
Series III. Notes
Boxes 5-12
Mostly handwritten by co-author A.J. Perkins, from many sources. Most of these are copied word for word from Fanny Wright letters although some are excerpts of letters. In chronological order except for the first 3 folders of notes from newspapers.
Series IV. Wright Documents
Box 13-14
Various speeches and lectures by Fanny Wright. These have been microfilmed (Film #5216) and should be used rather than originals due to their deteriorating condition.
Series V. Microfilm
Box 15
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - 1909-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1-19)
  - Undated correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Series II. Drafts
  - Introduction, n.d (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chapter l - A Fling at the Stars, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Chapter 2 - Fulfillment and Fiasco, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Chapter 3 - New Harmony - An Escape, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Chapter 4 - Educating the Masses, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - Chapter 5 - Priestess of Beelzebub, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Chapter 5 - continued, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Chapter 6 - Haiti and Europe, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - Chapter 7 - Phiquepal D'Arusmont & Marriage, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
  - Chapter 8 - The Swing of the Pendulum, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
  - Chapter 9 - no title, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Index and Bibliography, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Biography, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous unidentified segments, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
  - Draft corrections and suggestions, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Series III. Notes
  - New Harmony Gazette, 1925-1928 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Free Inquirer, 1928-1931 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper notes, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Notes, 1795-1820 (Box 5, Folder 5-14)
  - Notes, 1821-1823 (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
  - Notes, 1824-1827 (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
  - Notes, 1827-1828 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Notes, 1829-1836 (Box 9, Folder 1-10)
  - Notes, 1837-1878 (Box 10, Folder 1-19)
  - Notes, 1882-1930 (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
  - Undated notes, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 7-14)
  - Undated miscellaneous and index cards, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 15-16)
  - Poetry by Fanny Wright, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Index cards, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Series IV. Wright documents
  - Speeches and lectures (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
    -use microfilm
  - Speeches and lectures (Box 13, Folder 1-6)
  - Last Will and Testament (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Correspondences (Box 13, Folder 8-13)
  - Nashoba - Trust and Deed, Maps (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Nashoba - Address, 1827 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Nashville (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Agreements, 1761-1834 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Publications (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Clippings (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Series V. Microfilm
  - Copies of contents in Boxes 5-8, Reel 1 (Box 15)
  - Copies of contents in Boxes 8-14, Reel 2 (Box 15)
  - Copies of contents in Box 13, Reel 3 (Box 15)
  - Copies of contents in Box 13, Reel 4 (Box 15)
  - Speeches and lectures, Reel 5 (Box 15)